<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods call, for mans heart in 1 Knowledge, 2 Loue, 3 Feare, 4 Confidence, 5 Singing of Psalmes, 6 Prayer, 7 Hearing the word. 8 Receiuing the Sacraments. Deliuered in a sermon, by Abraham Iackson, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at Chelsey, neere London.</title>
            <author>Jackson, Abraham, 1589-1646?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14294</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854616</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854616</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20043</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20043)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1313:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods call, for mans heart in 1 Knowledge, 2 Loue, 3 Feare, 4 Confidence, 5 Singing of Psalmes, 6 Prayer, 7 Hearing the word. 8 Receiuing the Sacraments. Deliuered in a sermon, by Abraham Iackson, Master of Arts, and preacher of Gods word at Chelsey, neere London.</title>
                  <author>Jackson, Abraham, 1589-1646?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Roger Iackson, and are to be sould at his shop neere Fleetstreete Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The words "1 Knowledge .. the Sacraments" are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20043:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20043:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS CALL, FOR Mans Heart: <hi>Jn</hi> 
               <list>
                  <item>1 Knowledge,</item>
                  <item>2 Loue,</item>
                  <item>3 Feare,</item>
                  <item>4 Confidence,</item>
                  <item>5 Singing of Pſalmes,</item>
                  <item>6 Prayer,</item>
                  <item>7 Hearing the Word.</item>
                  <item>8 Receiuing the Sacraments.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Deliuered in a SERMON, by ABRAHAM IACKSON, Maſter of Arts, and
Preacher of Gods word at Chelſey, neere London.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 22.21.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Giue vnto God thoſe things which are Gods.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Roger
Iackson,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop neere Fleet-ſtreete
Conduit, 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20043:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20043:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE <hi>Edward</hi> Lord
<hi>Ruſſell,</hi> Earle of Bedford, and the Lady LVCIE Counteſſe of
Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford; ſuch felicitie in this life, as may end with the beginning of
thoſe ioyes that ſhall neuer end.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Moſt noble and truely religious Lord and
Lady:</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your vndeſerued fauour to me wards, challengeth my ſeruice
as a debt: ſo tho vnmerited mercies of God to vs all, requires our hearts as
a due. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the latter moued me to pen this Treatiſe: and the
conſideration of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, animated me to Dedicate it to your <pb facs="tcp:20043:3"/>Honours; not that there is any thing in it which you knew not before,
as hauing long ſince learned how to conſecrate your hearts vnto the Lord:
but to put you in minde of your knowledge, that you doe not forget to
practiſe it. All that the Lord requires of you, for whatſoeuer hee hath
beſtowed on you, is in effect but this, that you ſtudie to know him, to
loue him, to feare him, to truſt in him; that you ſing vnto him, pray vnto
him, heare his Word, and receiue his Sacraments with your hearts and ſoules,
as you ſhall finde briefely proued in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: which if you doe (as
all that obſerue your religious liues and conuerſations) are perſwaded
you doe,) you may reſt ſecure of Gods loue and fauour towards you in
Ieſus Chriſt, euen to the full aſſurance of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, which he
hath prepared for thoſe that giue him their hearts in his ſeruice. And ſo
crauing pardon for my boldneſſe, if in this Dedication I be delinquent, I
reſt:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours, ready in all humilitie to doe you
ſeruice, ABRAHAM IACKSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20043:3"/>
            <head>GODS CALL FOR MANS <hi>HEART.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 23.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q> 
                  <p>My Sonne, giue me thy Heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eaſt in this time of giuing and receiuing of gifts amongſt
friends, and acquaintances, you ſhould be vnmindefull of your beſt friend,
euen your God; <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20043:4"/>from whom whatſoeuer good and perfect gift
wee haue is deriued. <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17. I haue made choiſe of this
Scripture for the ſubiect of my ſpeech, the better to ſtirre you vp to
preſent vnto God (by way of gratefull acknowledgement of his loue and fauour)
the beſt Iewell, or (to vſe <hi>Dauids</hi> words) the beſt member that
you haue, euen your hearts; and the rather becauſe he requeſts them at your
hands, in the words of my Text; <hi>My ſonne, giue me thy heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a Sonne would gratifie his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or a friend his friend,
that loues him dearely, and out of his loue hath done much for him, he will
conſider with himſelfe what his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or his friend beſt likes, and
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly endeuour to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his power to prepare it for him.
Beloued, our gracious God <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20043:4"/>and mercifull redeemer, hath ſo
dearely loued vs, and done ſo much for vs, as that betweene his loue and
created affections, there holds no proportion. For, ſuppoſe ſome great
Prince ſhould ſet his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon ſome poore man, ſo farre as to
diſrobe himſelfe of his royall apparell, caſt off his Crowne, and ceaſe
to be a King, onely to inioy more freely this poore mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and
familiaritie; certainely it would be a great argument of loue. Nay, ſuppoſe
this Prince ſhould yet goe further in the manifeſtation of his loue, by
offering himſelfe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to die for this his poore friend; if his death
might be any way auaileable vnto him, as <hi>Damon,</hi> it may be, would haue
done for <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> or <hi>Pylades</hi> for <hi>Oreſtes;</hi> a
grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teſtification of loue there cannot be; and that by the teſtimony
of <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20043:5"/>our Sauiour, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.13. Where he ſaith,
<hi>That greater loue then this hath no man, when any man beſtoweth his life
for his friends.</hi> Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, all this loue comes far ſhort
of Chriſts loue towards vs: for he being the Prince of peace from all
eternitie, clad with the royall robes of glory, attended on with myriads of
bleſſed Angels, ſwaying the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the whole world, ſitting on
the right hand of his fathers maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie on high, meaſuring the waters in
his fiſt, and counting heauen with a ſpanne, and comprehending the duſt
of the earth in a meaſure, and weighing the mountaines in a weight, and the
hils in a ballance, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 40.12. This great Prince I ſay
(notwithſtanding all theſe preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues) was ſo inflamed with the loue
of vs poore creatures, the wretched broode of ſinfull <hi>Adam,</hi> 
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20043:5"/>lumpes of vanitie, maſſes of miſery, banquerupts in
reſpect of grace, and captiues to ſinne and Sathan; that he left the
brightneſſe of his fathers glorie, and tooke vpon him the vileneſſe of
our nature; he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare thundering in the cloudes, to crie in the cradle; he
left the ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſtarre-beautified chamber of heauen, to be lodg'd in
a ſtable, crowded in a cratch, and ſwadled in a few proore cloutes here on
earth: in a word, <hi>The Word was made fleſh and dwelt amongſt vs;</hi>
and yet this is not all: he did not onely take vpon him our fleſh, and our
nature, but our nakedneſſe, our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, our pouertie, our ſhame; nay,
(that which is yet beyond the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt and apprehenſion of men and Angels)
hee tooke vpon him our mortalitie; he made himſelfe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto death for
vs, euen to that <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20043:6"/>ſhamefull, painefull, racking,
tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, lingering death of the croſſe; he was crucified for vs, he had
his hands and his feet peirced and torne with nailes for vs, his head was
crowned with thorns for vs, his ſide and heart was wounded with a ſpeare
for vs, his hands, his feete, his head, his ſide, his heart guſht out with
ſtreames of bloud for vs, and that, <hi>cum adhuc inimici eſſemus,</hi>
when as yet we were his enemies. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7.8. <hi>Cum non ſolum non
exiſtentes, ſed etiam reſiſtentes,</hi> when we were not onely not
exiſtent, but reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent; euen his profeſſed foes, and mortall
enemies: When our hearts were as yet captiues to ſinne and Sathan, fighting
vnder their ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt him; he ſpent the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of his heart
to redeeme vs. Oh the exceeding loue of a gracious God, to an vngracious 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20043:6"/>people! infinite degrees beyond the affection of the
deareſt friend to his friend. Well then what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines to be done on our
part, but that (by way of gratefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of this his
vnproportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fauour) we preſent vnto him this day for a new-yeares gift,
the beſt member that we haue, euen our hearts; and the rather, becauſe he
askes them at our hands, as you may ſee in the words of my Text, <hi>My
Sonne, giue me thy heart.</hi> It may be called, <hi>Gods, demand of his
tribute due vnto him, from his children;</hi> or in fewer word, <hi>Gods call,
for Mans heart.</hi> In the which (for my better proceeding, and your better
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing) I haue thought good to obſerue theſe foure
circumſtances.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. What it is that God would haue, when he cals for our
<hi>Hearts.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20043:7"/>
               <item>II. The Perſons, whoſe harts God cals for, in theſe
words <hi>[My Sonne.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. The manner how he would haue theſe perſons Hearts,
in this word <hi>[Giue,]</hi> he would haue them by gift.</item>
               <item>IIII. The Perſon to whom hee would haue them giuen, in this
word <hi>[Mee,]</hi> he would haue them giuen to himſelf: <hi>My Sonne, giue
mee thy heart.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. That which God cals for, to be giuen vnto him, it is our
Hearts, <hi>My Sonne, giue mee thy Heart.</hi> That you may the better
vnderſtand what he meanes when he cals for our hearts, conſider I pray you
the ſeuerall acceptations of this word Heart. This word Heart, it is taken
either properly, or improperly. Firſt, properly, ſo it ſignifies that
diſſimilar part, that internall <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20043:7"/>pyramidall, or triangular
fleſhly ſubſtance within the body of man, which the Philoſophers call
the chaire of ſtate, or throne of the ſoule, the ſeate of the affections,
the conſiſtorie of mans thoughts and meditations, conceits and
imaginations, the fountaine of the vitall ſpirits, the firſt member of man
that liues, and the laſt that dies. Secondly, improperly, and ſo it is
taken either <hi>Synecdochically,</hi> or <hi>Metaphorically,</hi> or
<hi>Metonimically.</hi> Firſt, in a <hi>Synecdochicall</hi> acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it
ſignifies the whole man, as well his body as his ſoule; and in this ſence
our Sauiour vnderſtood it, when in <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. he bids vs, <hi>Take
heede leſt at any time our hearts be ouercome with ſurfetting and
drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes:</hi> Here the heart which is but a part of man, is by a
<hi>Synecdoche</hi> taken for the whole man, for drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20043:8"/>is hurtfull both to body and ſoule. Secondly,
<hi>Metaphorical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> ſo it ſignifies either the pith of a plant or
tree, by which vegetatiue life and motion is conueyed from the roote to the
branches, or elſe the courage and valour of a man, ſo that a ſtout and
valiant man is oftentimes called a Heart. Thirdly, <hi>Metonymically,</hi> and
ſo (if you take the ſubiect for the accidents) it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the
vnderſtanding and the ſinceritie of the affections of the heart. Now when
the Lord cals for our hearts, he cals not for them in a proper acceptation, nor
in an improper <hi>Synecdochycall</hi> or <hi>Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall</hi> ſence; but
(as I conceiue) chiefely, and principally, in a <hi>Meto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymicall</hi> meaning:
ſo that when the Lord cals for our hearts, he cals for our vnderſtanding,
for our loue, for our feare, for our confidence: hee <pb n="11" facs="tcp:20043:8"/>cals
for the ſinceritie of our hearts in ſinging of Pſalmes, in Prayer, in
hearing the Word, in receiuing the Sacraments: <hi>My Sonne, giue me thy
heart;</hi> that is, know me with thy heart, loue me with thy heart, feare me
with thy heart, truſt in me with thy heart, ſing vnto me with thy heart,
pray vnto me with thy heart, heare my word with thy heart, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the
Sacraments with thy heart: whatſoeuer thou doeſt in my ſeruice, doe it
with thy heart, and it ſhall be acceptable vnto me. So that when the Lord
requires our hearts, he requires the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of them in the performance
of theſe eight duties, as I ſhall indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to proue by ſeuerall places
of Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt we muſt ſtudie to know and vnderſtand what
God is, we muſt ſet the meditations of our <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20043:9"/>hearts aworke
about it.<note n="1" place="margin">1 Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> Hence is it that the
Lord promiſeth to giue his people <hi>A heart to know him to be the Lord.
Ier.</hi> 24.7. Whence I obſerue, that vnleſſe our hearts be inflamed
with a ſpeciall touch of grace to meditate vpon God, and to ſtudy to know
him, ſo farre forth as he is pleaſed to make himſelfe knowne in his word,
we can neuer giue him our hearts, as hee requires. Let vs then bend our hearts
to that end, for which he gaue them vnto vs. He gaue vs our hearts to ſtudie
to know him: Oh let vs render to him our hearts againe, by imploying our beſt
indeuours in this buſineſſe. Which we ſhall doe, if we be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
readers, hearers, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of his word, eſpecially that part of his
word, by which he is pleaſed to make himſelfe knowne vnto vs in his
Eſſence, Attributes, <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20043:9"/>Names and Actions.<note place="margin">If you medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on theſe places of Scripture, you ſhall be
well furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God.</note> When wee meete then with
any Scripture that deſcribes him either in the<note n="a" place="margin">Deut.
4.35. Deut. 6.4. Eſay 43.10. &amp; 44.6. &amp; 45.5. 1 Cor. 8.4. Gal. 3 20.
Epheſ. 4.6. 1 Tim. 2.5. Iam. 2.19.</note> Vnitie for his Eſſence, or in
the<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 6.3. Mat. 13.16.17. &amp; 28.9. Ioh.
14.16.17 1 Iob. 5.7.</note> Trinitie for the manner of his exiſtence; or in
his Attributes, either incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable, ſuch as are<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh 4.24. Heb. 12.9. 2 Cor. 3.17. Eſ. 31 3.</note>
ſimpleneſſe without mixture,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 90.2. &amp;
92.8.9. &amp; 102.27.28.</note> eternitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beginning,<note n="e" place="margin">1 King. 8.27. Ioh. 11.8. Pſ. 139.7.8. Ier. 23.24.</note>
immenſitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſ. 102.13.27. Mal.
3.6. Heb. 1.11.12. Iam. 1.17. Exod. 3.14.</note> immutabilitie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change;
or communicable, ſuch as are<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh 1.4. Deut. 32.40.
Dan 4.34.</note> life,<note n="h" place="margin">1 Tim 6.16.</note>
immortalitie,<note n="i" place="margin">Iob 12.13. Dan. 2.20. Rom. 11.33. 1 Tim.
1.17.</note>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 9.18.19.</note>
will,<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 17.1. Pſal. 62.12. Ier. 33.17.19. Luk.
1.37.49. Rom. 4.17.</note> power,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 115.3.</note>
liberty,<note n="n" place="margin">Mar. 9.18. Pſal. 118.1.2.3.4. Pſa. 108.5.
&amp; 31.20. Tit. 3.4.</note> goodneſſe,<note n="o" place="margin">Exod.
33.3.</note> grace,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.8.</note> loue,<note n="q" place="margin">Dan. 9 9.18 Exod. 34 6. Pſal. 116.5. &amp; 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.13. &amp; 146.8.9.</note>
mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 2.4. &amp; 3.26. &amp; 9.22. 1 Pet. 3.20.
2 Pet. 3.15.</note> patience,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ezek. 18.23. &amp;
33.11.</note> clemencie,<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 32.4. Pſal. 11.7.
&amp; 145.7 Apoc. 16.5.</note> iuſtice,<note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.2.
Eſ. 6.3. Hab. 1.12.13.1 Ioh. 1.5. Apoc. 4.8.</note> holineſſe, and<note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 10.17.1 Cron. 29.11.12. Pſal. 83.19.1 Tim. 6.15. 
<p>You may ſee a plaine deſcription of Gods Eſſence, and
Attributes in <hi>The Practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e of
Pietie,</hi> ſet forth by Docter <hi>Bayly,</hi> now Biſhop of
<hi>Bangor,</hi> from the 4. page, of the eight Edition, to the 59.</p>
               </note>
glory: or in any <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20043:10"/>of his Names, Titles or actions; we
ſhould meditate on it, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it deepely in our hearts, wee ſhould
treaſure it vp in our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and walke as in the ſight of his ſo awfull
and diume Maieſtie. If thus we indeauour to know him, we giue him one chiefe
thing which he requires, when he requires our hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. Loue.</note>When the Lord cals for our
hearts, he cals for the loue of our hearts. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Thou
ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, and
with all thy might.</hi> Now he that loues God with his heart and ſoule, will
delight to be in his houſe ſometimes, lauding and magnifying his name with
the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of his Saints, ſometimes talking with him by meditation and
prayer; hee will eſteeme Gods loue and fauour dearer then his life.
<hi>Pſa.</hi> 
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20043:10"/>63.2. He will bewaile his abſence in
disfauour as a bitter croſſe. <hi>Can.</hi> 3.1. He will hate thoſe that
hate God, &amp; loue thoſe that loue God; he will hate wickedneſſe,
becauſe God hates it, and hate wicked men, becauſe they hate God: he will
loue righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, becauſe God loues it, and he will loue righteous
men, becauſe they loue God: hee will be more ſenſible of Gods
diſhonour, then of his owne diſgrace: he will loue the image of God in
wiſedome, in knowledge, in vprightneſſe of life, (though he finde it in a
poore and deiected man, in reſpect of this world) more deare then any friend
can loue the picture of his friend: Theſe, and the like are the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of that man that loues God with all his heart, and with all his ſoule. But if
we take no delight to be in the houſe of God, if it be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous 
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20043:11"/>vnto vs to diſcourſe with him by Prayer, and
Meditation; if we preferre either our eaſe, or our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or our
pleaſure, or our liues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fauvour; if wee can thinke our ſelues
happy to be out of his ſight, if we can finde a delightfull recreation in the
mad meriments of wicked men, if we can hate that which he loues, and loue that
which he hates; if we can be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to preſerue our owne credits,
then Gods honour; nay, if we can loue the image of the diuell in men, drawne to
the life with the penſill of iniquitie, then are not we the men that loue the
Lord; wee may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with our tongues that we loue him, but our hearts
will giue our tongues the lye, becauſe wee loue him not with our hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="3" place="margin">3. Feare.</note>When God would haue our
hearts, he would haue our feare; <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20043:11"/>
               <hi>My Sonne, giue me thy
heart;</hi> that is, giue me the feare of thy heart, or feare me with thy
heart. Hence is that <hi>Samuel</hi> exhorts the people to offer vp vnto God
the feare of their hearts, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Feare you the Lord, and
ſerue him in the truth, with all your hearts, &amp;c.</hi> And in
<hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Moſes</hi> tels the Iſraelites, that the Lord
requireth nothing elſe at their hands; but to <hi>feare him, and walke in his
waies, to loue him, and ſerue him with all their hearts, and with all their
ſoules.</hi> Queſtionleſſe there is none of you that heare me this day,
but will ſay he feares God with all his heart; but it is not inough to ſay
ſo, vnleſſe it appeare ſo by tryall. Well then, if thou feare the Lord
with thy heart, certainely thy feare will be filiall, it will be ſuch as the
feare of a ſonne in reſpect of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; thou wilt be more fearefull 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20043:12"/>to offend him, then to beare the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of offence:
thou wilt be fearefull to commit any ſinne in priuate, or in the darke,
becauſe thou art certaine the eye of God is vpon thee: thou wilt be more
trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the threats of Gods Word, then at the checks of a mortall Man,
though he be thy Prince. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.161. Thou wilt with the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues,
<hi>Exod.</hi> 1.17. with the three Children, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.16. with holy
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, Dan.</hi> 6.10. with the zealous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.19.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 5.29 and with faithfull <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 22.12. feare, and
worſhip, and obey God, though it be prejudiciall to thy eaſe, to thy
profit, to thy preferment, to thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, to thy life, though it croſſe
thy reaſon, thy affection, thy hope, thy expectation, in future times. But if
thy feare be ſlauiſh; if thou feare more the puniſhment, then 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20043:12"/>the offence; if thou care not what wickedneſſe thou
commit, ſo that the eye of man be not vpon thee; if thou be ready to doe that
which a wicked <hi>Ieroboam</hi> ſhall command thee, though it be neuer ſo
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God, fearing a temporall puniſhment more then an
eternall condemnation: if thou refuſe to obey ſuch of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
as doe any way croſſe thy eaſe, thy profit, thy pleaſure, thy reaſon,
thy eſtimation with men, or the like; certainely, thou doeſt not as yet
feare God with thy heart, and therefore thou haſt not as yet any heart for
God.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="4" place="margin">4. Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note>When God cals for
our hearts, he cals for our truſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence: <hi>My Sonne, giue me thy
heart,</hi> that is, relie vpon mee with thy heart, lay thy truſt and
confidence on mee with thy heart: Thus did <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20043:13"/>
               <hi>Dauid</hi>
giue God his heart, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 130.5. <hi>I haue waited on the Lord</hi>
(ſaith he) <hi>My ſoule hath waited, and I haue truſted in his word.</hi>
And againe, in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 28.7 he ſaith thus, <hi>The Lord is my
ſtrength and my ſhield, mine heart truſted in him, and I was helped;
therefore mine heart ſhall reioyce, and with my ſong will I praiſe
him.</hi> And as <hi>Dauid</hi> truſted in the Lord, ſo muſt we: <hi>We
muſt truſt in the Lord with all our hearts, and not leane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne
wiſedome, Pro.</hi> 3.5. We muſt haue recourſe vnto him, as to our onely
ſhield and buckler to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs againſt the oppoſitions of our
ſpirituall and temporall aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, as to our onely helpe to ſaue and
deliuer vs in all our diſtreſſes, and as to our onely preſeruer, to
giue vs all good and neceſſarie bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, both for body and ſoule:
We muſt relie vpon him, wait vpon <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20043:13"/>him, and repoſe our
truſt in him without reſpect either to reaſon, to meanes, or likelyhoods.
This if we doe, we truſt in the Lord with our hearts: But if when we ſee no
out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes of helpe, we faile in our hopes, as the Iſraelites did,
<hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.20. If when we are ſick, we ſend for the Phyſician
before wee ſeeke to God, as <hi>Aſa</hi> did, 2 <hi>Cro.</hi> 16.12. If
when ſome bone of ſinnes body doth as it were ſticke in the throat of our
guiltie conſciences, we hope to waſh it downe with a cuppe of Sacke, as
many lewd ſurfetters on pleaſure doe. If when we be in any ſtrait, we
make fleſh our arme, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.5. If we repoſe our truſt in our
owne or others with and policie, in our owne or others ſtrength. <hi>If we
ſay to the wedge of gold, thou art my confidence, Iob</hi> 31.24. or to the
ſword thou art my ſafegard, or to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20043:14"/>thou art
my health, or 
<q>Flectere ſinequeo ſuperos Acheronta mouebo.</q> if God
forſake me, if nature for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, ile goe to Egypt for helpe,
<hi>Iſ.</hi> 31.1. nay to hell for helpe: ile ſee what Croſſing can
doe, what Holy water can doe, what Popes pardons can doe: and if all this will
not doe, ile haue recourſe to Charmes and Exorciſmes, to Spels and
Incantati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c. If with the Prince of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael wee will not beleeue
<hi>Eliſha,</hi> I meane Gods Miniſters, when out of the word they
promiſe vs preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſupport, againſt the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and
croſſes of this world, againſt famine and want, and ſay as he did, 2
<hi>Ki.</hi> 7.2. <hi>Though the Lord would make windowes in heauen, can this
thing come to paſſe?</hi> If we will truſt God no further then we ſee
him, either actually reaching vnto vs his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:20043:14"/>or
laying before vs the meanes probable in our conceit to attaine them, then doe
we not truſt in him with our hearts, becauſe wee relye not on him without
reſpect to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, meanes, or likelyhoods.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="5" place="margin">5. Singing of Pſalmes</note>When the
Lord calles for our Hearts, hee calles for our hearts in ſinging: when we
ſing Pſalmes, we muſt ſing with our hearts. To this the holy Ghoſt
exhorts vs by the pen of the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. when hee bids vs
<hi>Sing to the Lord with a grace in our hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M.
Byfield <hi>ſuper locum</hi>
               </note> that is (as a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; iudicious
Diuine expounds it) 
<q>Wee muſt exerciſe the graces of our hearts in ſinging;
<hi>Wee muſt ſing to the Lord,</hi> that is, with an eye to his glory, with
ſence of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, with commemoration of his bleſſings; and wee
muſt ſing <hi>with our hearts,</hi> not with our tongues onely, outwardly
for oſtentation, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:20043:15"/>but with vnderſtanding,
<hi>Pſa.</hi> 47.7 with ſence and feeling: Hence is it that our hearts are
to be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before wee ſing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7. and hence is it that
<hi>Dauid</hi> bids his tongue awake, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.8. noting that he
obſerued in men a lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; not a hoarſeneſſe in voyce, but a
ſlumber in heart, when they vſed the voyce. <hi>We muſt therefore ſing
to the Lord with our hearts,</hi> yea <hi>with the graces of our hearts,</hi>
that is, with a holy ioy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.2. with truſt in Gods mercyes,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.5. with a holy commemoration of his benefits,
<hi>Pſ.</hi> 47.6. yea, with the prayer and deſires of our hearts, that our
words in ſinging may be acceptable, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.33.34.</q>
Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading our ſelues that it is not the ſweet voyce, but the zealous
vow, not the harmonious ſound, but the hearts ſoundneſſe that makes
melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <pb n="25" facs="tcp:20043:15"/>in the eares of God; expreſt by the Poet thus: 
<q>
                  <l>Non vox ſed votum, non muſica chordula ſed cor,</l> 
                  <l>Non clamans ſed amans clangit in aure Dei.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But if we ſing Pſalmes as we doe common Songs and Ballads,
more to delight our owne &amp; others eares, then to teſtifie our gratefull
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of Gods mercyes: If we ſing more for ordinary recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,
then for zealous deuotion: If we reſpect more the muſick then the matter:
If wee care not how harſh the intention of our hearts be, ſo our voyces be
tunable; wee ſing not to the Lord with ſuch a grace in our hearts as hee
requires, wee giue him not our hearts in ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:20043:16"/>
            <p>
               <note n="6" place="margin">6. Prayer.</note>The Lord calles for our
hearts in Prayer. When we pray we muſt pray with our hearts. This
<hi>Dauid</hi> knew well, when in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17. hee ſaith, that
<hi>God will not deſpiſe a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and contrite heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence I obſerue, that (becauſe the prayers which proceede
from a broken and contrite heart are neuer ſlighted by the Lord) when wee
pray, if we hope to ſpeede, we muſt pray with a broken heart, with a
wounded ſpirit: When wee offer vp any petition to the Lord (if we expect an
anſwere) wee muſt offer vp our hearts: For if we offer our lips inſteade
of our hearts, it is no meruaile if God giue vs ſtones in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of bread,
that is, a ſhadow of comfort, inſtead of reall comfort. <hi>Non labia
vitulorum, ſed vituli labio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> It is not the calues lippes, but
<hi>the calues of our lippes, Oſe.</hi> 14.3. that <pb n="27" facs="tcp:20043:16"/>are
acceptable to God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ille magis gratae laetatur mentis odore,</l> 
               <l>Quam conſecrato ſanguine mille boum:</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hee is more delighted with the ſweet odour of a gratefull
breſt, then with the ſacrificed bloud of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Oxen. God is not
like a childe to be wonne with faire words; nor like the people of
<hi>Tyrus</hi> and <hi>Sydon, Act.</hi> 12.21.22. that were rauiſhed with
<hi>Herods</hi> eloquent Oration: for hee eſteemes no more of the
quain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt oratorie, if it come not from the heart, then of the lowing of an
oxe, or the houling of a dog. It is not the length, or well-coucht phraſes in
a prayer, but the zealous heart of him that prayes, which God regards: for hee
eſteemed more of the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes foure words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>O.
God be mercifull to me a <pb n="28" facs="tcp:20043:17"/>ſinner, Luke</hi> 18.13. and of
<hi>Dauids</hi> three ſillables, <hi>Peccaui,</hi> I haue ſinned; nay, of
the <hi>Haimoriſſes</hi> touch, though without words or ſillables,
becauſe they proceeded from a broken and wounded ſpirit, then of the
Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes long and tedious gratulation, <hi>Lu.</hi> 18.9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
If then (when thou feeleſt within thee a trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) thou
goeſt to God in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, and with <hi>Hanna,</hi> poureſt out thy ſoule
before him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.19. If with <hi>Dauid</hi> thou ſupplicate and
cry vnto him with thy whole heart, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.58.145. If with
<hi>Ieremie,</hi> thou lift vp thy heart with thy hands, and poure it out like
water before his face, <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.41. doubt not but
he will accept thy ſacrifice, yea, though thou want words to expreſſe thy
ſuite: if thou canſt ſobbe, and ſigh (though thou be not able to vtter
thy minde) thou <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20043:17"/>maiſt be perſwaded that the Spirit
vnderſtandeth thy meaning, and that thoſe bitter ſighes and ſobbes
comming from the Spirit, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile with God for the obtaining of thy
petition; for why, <hi>a broken and contrite heart, the Lord will not
deſpiſe:</hi> when thou praieſt, therefore pray with thy heart.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="7" place="margin">7. Hearing of the Word.</note>The Lord
requires our hearts in the hearing of his Word, and therefore in <hi>Luk.</hi>
8.15. he makes the hearing of the Word with a good heart, a note of the beſt
hearers, comparing them to the beſt ground that brings forth the beſt
fruit. Hence it is alſo that <hi>Dauid</hi> inclined his heart vnto Gods
Teſtimonies, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.36. and hid his word in his heart, that he
might not ſinne. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.11. When then we come to Church, we
ſhould ſettle our harts; that is, our
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffections, our zeales, 
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20043:18"/>our attentions, to heare the Word either redde or preached.
When Chriſt puts his hand to the hole of the dore, our hearts ſhould (with
the ſpouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioned towards him. When he
talkes with vs by the way of this our pilgrimage, our hearts, with the two
Diſciples that went to <hi>Emaus,</hi> ſhould burne within vs. When the
Miniſter of Gods word is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his meſſage, which the Lord hath put
into his mouth, we ſhould with the noble Emperour
<hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. lib.
<hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> be ſo rauiſhed
with thoſe things which we heare, as that we attend to nothing elſe: Our
thoughts ſhould not be diſtracted with vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of worldly
buſineſſes: our eyes ſhould not be poſſeſt with ſlumber; our
taſte (in reſpect of the Word) ſhould not be like old
<hi>Barzillais,</hi> without reliſh; we muſt not thinke <pb n="31" facs="tcp:20043:18"/>of Sermons, as <hi>Naaman</hi> did of <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> 2
<hi>King.</hi> 5.11. but we muſt haue them in a reuerend regard; we muſt
ſettle our ſelues to heare, and heare to vnderſtand, and vnderſtand to
practice, and practice to attaine an habituall obedience to the precepts of
holy life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="8" place="margin">8. Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the
Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>Laſtly, the Lord would haue vs offer vp our hearts vnto
him, when we receiue the Sacrament. It is not then but vpon good ground, that
the Miniſter (before the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper) exhorts the
people to lift vp their hearts,<note place="margin">Miniſters exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</note> and the people an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <hi>wee lift them vp
vnto the Lord:</hi> or to vſe the words of the Prophet, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.1.
<hi>Vnto thee O Lord, lift we vp our ſoules.</hi> Well is it then which the
Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſaith, that the onely way to receiue the Lords
Supper worthily, is to lift vp <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20043:19"/>our minds by faith aboue all
things worldly and ſenſible, and thereby to enter into heauen, that we may
finde and receiue Chriſt where he dwelleth. We muſt not thinke (as the
Papiſts vainely imagine) that we hold Chriſt bodily in our hands, and
maſticate him in our mouthes, when we receiue and eat the Bread; but
receiuing the Bread and Wine, as the ſymboles of his body and bloud, we
ſhould lift vp our hearts to heauen, where he ſitteth at the right hand of
his father, and where he muſt continue till the time that all things are
reſtored, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.21. And thus much be ſpoken of the matter of Gods
demand; namely, of that which he requires at our hands, when he cals for our
hearts, <hi>My Sonne, giue mee thy heart;</hi> that is, apply thy heart vnto me
in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the Sacraments, in hearing <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20043:19"/>the Word, in
Prayer, in ſinging of Pſalmes, ſettle thy heart to depend on me, to feare
me, to loue me, to know me: Me I ſay, that haue done for thee then any
created vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding can conceiue.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And ſo I paſſe from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what muſt be
giuen, to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that muſt giue, expreſt in theſe words <hi>[My
Sonne.]</hi> The Lord cals for the hearts of his children: <hi>My Sonne, giue
me thy heart.</hi> Whence I obſerue, that a childe of God owes no leſſe
to his heauenly father, then his heart. For if a ſeruant owe his induſtry
to his maiſter, that paies him his hire; if a Sonne owe his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his
Parents that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides him maintenance: if a ſubiect owne his allegiance to
his Prince, that defends him from theeues, in reſpect of his goods, and from
mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, in reſpect of his life; I ſee <pb n="34" facs="tcp:20043:20"/>no reaſon,
why we that ſtand in the relation of Seruants, of Sonnes, of Subiects, of
things of nothing, of things worſe then nothing vnto God, as our Creator, our
Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer or Maſter, our Father, our King, our Protector or defender:
ſhould not be ſo much indebted vnto him as our hearts comes too, as our
ſoules comes too, as all that is within vs comes too. We owe then to God, no
leſſe then our hearts; if they were not his due, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer demand
them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vſe, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</note>By this Doctrine
we may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelues whether we be the children of God or no: for if we
can be perſwaded in conſcience, that we owe our hearts to God, and
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly indeauour to pay them, we may be certaine, that we ſtand in the
relation of ſonnes vnto God: but if we cannot finde in our hearts 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20043:20"/>to beſtow our hearts on God: if there be an
indiſpoſition in vs to know him, to loue him, to feare him, to truſt in
him, with all our hearts, and with all our ſoules: if we can ſing with our
voyce pray with our lippes, heare with our eares, receiue the Sacrament with
our mouthes, and not ſing, pray, heare, and receiue the bleſſed
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with our hearts; certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we cannot as yet take any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in
Gods election, becauſe we cannot certainely be perſwaded that we are his
ſonnes, in that we are not willing to pay vnto him that tribute which his
ſonnes owe vnto him, we preſent not our hearts vnto him by way of gift,
which is the third circumſtance of my Text; namely, the manner how we are to
beſtow our hearts on God, expreſt in this word <hi>[Giue.]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20043:21"/>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>My Sonne, giue me thy heart;</hi> that is, giue it
mee. 
<list>
                  <item>1. Inſtantly, without delay.</item>
                  <item>2. Wholy, with out reſeruation.</item>
                  <item>3. And freely, without repining.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, we muſt giue our hearts vnto God inſtantly,
without delay: for ſo much the words <hi>Cedò,</hi> or <hi>Prebe</hi>
import: giue me thy heart preſently, or out of hand, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou goe
out of the Church. The Lord is impatient of delaies, we muſt therfore be as
quick in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering his call, as an Eccho in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling our voyce. This
quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was in <hi>Dauid,</hi> when the Lord bad him <hi>ſeeke his
face,</hi> hee anſwers like an eccho, <hi>Thy face Lord will I ſeeke,
Pſal.</hi> 27.9. Euen ſo beloued, now that the Lord bids vs giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him
our hearts, let vs inſtantly anſwer him, O Lord we giue thee our hearts.
Many would take a <pb n="37" facs="tcp:20043:21"/>day with the Lord for giuing vp their
hearts; they are loath to part with them vpon the ſodaine. The poore man
would be borne withall till he be rich; the rich man, till he be ſicke; the
ſicke man, till he haue recouered his health; the healthy and ſtrong man,
till he be weake; the weake and feeble man, till he be ſtrong againe; the
young man, till he be old; the old man, till he feele the ſignes of death;
the laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious man, till his luſt be ſatisfied; the enuious man, till he
be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on his enemie; the Merchant, till his trade be good; the Parent,
till his children be prouided for; the childe, till he haue his patrimony in
his owne diſpoſe; the ſeruant, till he be a maſter; and the maſter,
till he haue ſeruants to his owne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then certainely God ſhall
haue their hearts: But, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:20043:22"/> 
               <q>Qui non eſt hodie, cras minus aptus erit.</q> Hee that is not
willing to part with his heart to day, will be leſſe willing to morrow: For
the longer hee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers his heart to be in the poſſeſſion of his
eaſe, or his profit, or his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; hee ſhall with the more
diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty get it out of their fingers, to beſtow it on God. Indeed if it
were in our owne powers to take our hearts from pleaſure and vanitie, &amp;
giue them to God at our liſt, there might be ſome colourable reaſon for
delay; or if wee had each of vs two hearts, wee might aduenture one, to ſee
what would come of it: But ſeeing God hath giuen to each of vs one onely
heart, and that heart not in our own power neither to be ſtow on God when we
wil; we ſhuld be afraid to keepeit from him when hee calles for it. Oh then
my deare <pb n="39" facs="tcp:20043:22"/>chriſtian Brethren, let vs for euer take heed,
leſt if with <hi>Argus,</hi> we liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en too long to the <hi>Mercury</hi>
pipe of Gods long-ſuffering, we be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a dead ſleepe of
ſecuritie, to the vtter ſeperation of our hearts from God. Delayes (as for
the moſt part in our ciuill negotiation with men, ſo euermore, and
eſpecially, in our ſpirituall commerce with God) are very dangerous. If God
would not haue vs ſay vnto our neighbour, <hi>goe and come againe, and to
morrow I will giue thee,</hi> if we now haue that which hee deſires, and wee
can well ſpare, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.28. much leſſe when he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
aſkes our hearts for himſelfe, will hee be patient of a repulſe till to
morrow, much leſſe till a weeke be ouer, much leſſe till a month be
ouer, much leſſe till a yeere be ouer, much leſſe till old age, and
dotage, and weakeneſſe, and ſickneſſe, and <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20043:23"/>death
ſeaze vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Let vs conſider Gods caſe by our owne. If we be delayd in our
ſuites, if our expectation be put off from day to day, are not our hearts in
a manner alienated from them on whom our hope depends? <hi>Are not our hearts
poſſeſt with faintneſſe? Pro.</hi> 13.12. How much more ſhould we
thinke will God be auerſe from vs, if wee repell his ſuite for our hearts
with delayes? Oh then let vs ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice our hearts vnto him, <hi>whileſt it
is called to day,</hi> leſt if wee ſtay till to morrow, hee will not
receiue them, though we preſent them with tears.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Againe, God requires that we giue him our hearts, not
onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly without delay, but wholy without reſeruation: <hi>My
ſonne, giue me thy heart,</hi> that is, thy whole heart: not one peece to
day, and another to morrow, but all at once: not <pb n="41" facs="tcp:20043:23"/>halfe thy
heart, but all thy heart; <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. Many of vs I feare are like a woman
that hath many ſutors, who (willing to giue them all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent) ſpeakes
louingly to one, ſmiles vpon another, winkes vpon a third, and entertaines
the fourth, and the fift, and ſo the reſt, with ſome ſuch other glaunce
or geſture of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and yet notwithſtanding ſhee would make her
huſband beleeue that he hath her heart: Euen ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, although wee haue
in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſolempnely betrothed our hearts and ſoules vnto our Lord and
Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and haue promiſed to forſake the Diuell, the
World, &amp; the Fleſh, and to reſerue our ſoules as chaſte Brides for
his bed; yet when the world ſhal haunt our company, and preſent vs with a
mappe of his vanityes, when the Fleſh ſhall aſſaile vs, when any kind 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20043:24"/>of ſinne ſhall offer vs either profit or pleaſure, to
pollute our hearts with impure ſpawne; wee will ſpeake one faire, wincke
vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and entertaine the reſt with ſome ſecret ſmile or glance
of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour; thinking neuertheleſſe to make our Sauiour beleeue that he
onely hath our hearts: Indeede if his knowledge were like mans, he might be
deceiued with ſhewes and proteſtations: but ſeeing he alone is the
almighty heart-ſearcher, hee alone knowes the deceit and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of
theſe proteſtations; he ſees that we loue him ſcarce with halfe an
heart, and therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorces himſelfe from vs, and turnes vs ouer to our
owne lewdneſſe: he muſt haue all our hearts, or none at all. Suppoſe a
man ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Creditor halfe the money which he owes him, is it
likely that <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20043:24"/>it would be accepted, eſpecially when he
knowes his Debtor to be of abilitie to pay all? How much leſſe then
ſhould we imagine that God will accept of halfe our hearts, when we owe him
all, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when he giues abilitie to pay all? The vnnaturall
Mother would haue the childe deuided, but the naturall Mother, rather then
ſhee would yeelde to that, offered to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne her intereſt to the other,
1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3.28. So the Diuell tels vs he would haue but halfe our hearts,
and that God ſhould haue the other: but God will accept of no ſuch
conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; he ſcornes to part ſtakes with the Diuell: if the Diuell haue
one halfe, let him take the other too: God can indure no Copeſmate; he muſt
haue all, or none at all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eely too, without grudging, without repining. We <pb n="44" facs="tcp:20043:25"/>muſt not anſwere God when he cals for our hearts as <hi>Nabal</hi>
anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Dauids</hi> meſſengers, when they intreated prouiſion of
meat for their Maſter and themſelues, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. But we muſt
giue our hearts as freely as we would giue any thing to our friend, that is in
our owne poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But ſoft, it were not amiſſe if I propounded a queſtion:
Haue all of vs that are here preſent hearts to giue or no? or rather are not
ſome of vs here without hearts? yes certainely: If there be amongſt vs any
Worldling, or voluptuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or Epicure, or Drunkard, or Cheator, or
buſie-bodie, or enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſon, or the like, they are here without their
hearts. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous mans heart is where his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is; <hi>Where your
treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo:</hi> The Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20043:25"/>mans heart is where his wenches are: the Epicures heart is
where his dainties are: the Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards heart is where good liquor is: the
Cheaters heart is where game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are; the buſie-bodies heart is where
contentions are; and the enuious mans heart is where the perſon is whom he
hates. If there be any ſuch here (as it may be there are,) Oh call home your
hearts while it is called to day, and to day preſent them as an acceptable
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to him that hath long ſince bought them with the precious bloud
of his deare Sonne.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. And ſo I come to the fourth and laſt
circumſtance of my Text, which is the Perſon to whom we are to giue our
hearts, ſet downe in this word <hi>[Mee,] My Sonne, giue Mee thy heart.</hi>
Whence I obſerue, that God onely is the primary, and <pb n="46" facs="tcp:20043:26"/>chiefe obiect of our hearts, and ſo (by a conſequence) of our
vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, wills, and affections. Of our vnderſtandings,
becaúſe the chiefeſt truth: of our wills and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, becauſe
the chiefeſt good. Other things there are, about which thoſe faculties may
lawfully be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: as for example, the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding may bee exerciſed
about the knowledge of the vniuerſall and generall, ſingular and
indiuiduall natures of ſubſtances and accidents; as alſo about the
images, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and priuations of thoſe reall beings. And as the
Vnderſtanding, ſo the Will and Affections may (in a degree) be taken vp
about other Obiects, as about Vertue, lawfull profit, and lawfull pleaſure;
but not ſo as to ſeeke for perfect happineſſe in the one or in the
other: For God onely (as being onely infinite) is <pb n="47" facs="tcp:20043:26"/>the onely
ſatiſfactorie Obiect, in whom alone, and in nothing elſe true felicitie
is to be found.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhould be a ſtrong
motiue vnto vs to direct our hearts (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all their powers, motions,
and affections) chiefely and prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily vnto God. Other things wee may meditate
on, and deſire, ſo far foorth as they hould a candle vnto vs, and pricke vs
forward to the primary and onely true Obiect: But God alone muſt be the
white, to which wee all muſt ayme; the Ocean wherevnto the riuers of our
affections muſt all flow; and the Center wherein the lines of our beſt
indeauours muſt all meete. That man that loues his daughter will be carefull
to beſtow her in marriage vpon ſuch a one as deſires her for loue, and
out of his loue will aſſure <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20043:27"/>her a good ioynture: But if
hee hate his daughter, hee will not care what becomes of her; hee will giue his
conſent to any that ſhall make loue vnto her. Oh then my deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued
Brethren, if you loue your hearts beſtow them on God, that aſkes them for
loue, that aſkes them not for any benefit to himſelfe but for aduantage
vnto them; that aſkes them to inrich and beautifie them with the iewels &amp;
ornaments of ſauing graces here in this world, and to indow them with the
crown of euerlaſting bleſſedneſſe in the world to come.</p>
            <p>But if you hate your hearts, let either the world haue them, that
they may become ſtages for Folly, theaters for Vanitie, beds for Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,
conſiſtories for Deceipt, and chaires for Pride: or let the fleſh haue
them, that they may be ſeates <pb n="49" facs="tcp:20043:27"/>for Idleneſſe, anvills
for Lewdneſſe, tables for Epicuriſme, furnaces for Luſt; or let all
manner of ſinne and impietie haue them, that there may be liberty giuen to
Sathan to make Schoole-houſes of them, wherein to read lectures of
Atheiſme, of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, of Superſtition, of Blaſphemy, of Prophanation,
of Diſobedience, of Vncleanneſſe, of Couſenage, of Oppreſſion, of
Drunkenneſſe, of Luxury, of Riot, and the like, till they become meere
Chaoſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and vaſſals of damnation, to burne for euer as
neuer-periſhing Salamanders, in the red vengeance of endleſſe tortures:
from which the Lord of his infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye deliuer vs all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
